<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of obedience especially vnto authoritie ecclesiasticall, wherein the principall controuersies of our church are handled, and many of their obiections which are refractorie to the gouernment established, answered, though briefly as time and place could permit: being preached at a visitation of the right worshipfull M.D. Hinton,in Couentry. By Fran: Holyoke.</title>
            <author>Holyoake, Francis, 1567-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850695</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1521:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of obedience especially vnto authoritie ecclesiasticall, wherein the principall controuersies of our church are handled, and many of their obiections which are refractorie to the gouernment established, answered, though briefly as time and place could permit: being preached at a visitation of the right worshipfull M.D. Hinton,in Couentry. By Fran: Holyoke.</title>
                  <author>Holyoake, Francis, 1567-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold by Iohn Barnes [in London] dwelling neere Holborne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel title page and different imprint, of STC 13622.</note>
                  <note>Bookseller's address from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hinton, William, 1552 or 3-1631.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15919:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon of Obedience, Eſpecially vnto Authoritie Eccleſiaſticall, wherein the principall controuerſies of our <hi>Church are handled, and many of their</hi> Obiections which are refractorie to <hi>the gouernment eſtabliſhed, anſwered,</hi> though briefly as time and place could permit: Being preached at a Viſitation of the right Worſhipfull M.D. <hi>Hinton,</hi> in <hi>Couentry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> FRAN: HOLYOKE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ioſeph Barnes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Barnes</hi> dwelling neere Holborne Conduit. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15919:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. F. H.</hi> I haue pervſed your ſermon; for the plainenes of words and ſentences like your ſelfe, who naturally are an enimy to curioſity. For matter ſound, and the doctrine neceſſary, both for the time, &amp; eſpecially for that place. I knowe what tumultuous rumors it bred; and how it was by many more hainouſly taken then either hereſie or treaſon: how they traduced you and imagined what evill they could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, as both many in that Citty and the whole Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout can well witneſſe. And yet as you ſaid you knewe no cauſe why, vnleſſe it were for that one voice which you vrged among them to wit <hi>Obedience,</hi> a word indeed harſh ſounding in the eares of humoriſts, and eſpecially to them in that place, who chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by preſcription. And howſoeuer me thought, you touched them more neere the quick, the laſt time you prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched there before, which was at the laſt Viſitation of the late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhop deceaſed, yet this was more hainouſly taken; for they ſay that none but you, euer durſt preſume ſo much in that place being a ſtranger, to preach a doctrine which before hand you knew would be ſo offenſiue; and where as ignorance of their humors at firſt might be ſome excuſe, yet this now muſt needs be great preſumption. If the whole Citty ſhould bee gouerned by men of that faction, there would be an odde gouernment. As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a yeere or two ſince, when ſome of them were in ſpeciall autority: one of them pulled downe the picture of Chriſt from the market croſſe, as a monument of ſuperſtition, hauing beene there many many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeeres; &amp; placed in the rome the pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of an naked woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, til many of the graue ancients of the Citty ſeeing the abſurdity; cauſed it to bee taken down &amp; the Princes armes to be ſet in place. Another broke in peeces and defaced the picture of a doue which had hung ouer the font, time out of minde. No marvell therefore if that ſort of giddie heads would haue pulled you out of the pulpit, as ſince
<pb facs="tcp:15919:3"/> ſome of them haue profeſſed, they had purpoſed. That it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto all men what this ſermon was, that raiſed ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I haue publiſhed it not altogether againſt your minde, that it might anſwere for it ſelfe. And knowing that you owe even more then your ſelfe to that worthy Gentleman your Patron, I haue prefixed his name by way of Dedication; without other epistle, for I knowe if you were to write vnto him your ſelfe, you could neither expreſſe your harty affection towards him, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts towards you, nor his worthineſſe, as well for the execution of iuſtice in his place, as for his vprightneſſe every way, for his ſetled iudgement in religion and his integrity of practiſe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing himſelfe an example of obedience in all things. God bleſſe your ſtudies that you may profit Gods Church and preſent him your ſelfe with greater matters hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thoſe few things which you adde in the ende, which you told me you could not then deliuer for want of time; I haue marked them with this marke,, in the margent that no caveller may find ſhew to except that this is not the ſame which you deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing friend I.D.H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15919:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF OBEDIENCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 13.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Obey them that haue the ouerſight of you, &amp; ſubmit your ſelues for they watch for your ſoules as they that muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, that they may doe it with ioy and not with griefe, for that is vnprofitable for you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wil not now ſpend time to diſcuſſe who was the writer of this epiſtle, which is confeſſed almoſt of all to bee canonicall. For as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Gregorie vpon Iob ſaith it is to no purpoſe to ſearch and enquire who is the writer of that booke, of which we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the holy Ghoſt to be the author.</p>
            <p>This 13. Chapter containeth in it many exhortations to the performance of the duties of the ſecond table co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our loue to our neighbour. And in this 17, verſe is a ſpeciall exhortation to honor and obey our ſuperiors, which is the firſt and principall commandement of the ſecond table, hauing this prerogatiue to be the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement with promiſe. For the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by ſome to be civill magiſtrates, of others, to bee Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall gouernors. The word (as the great greeke Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologiſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15919:4"/> doth expound it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>one that is chiefe of a tribe, ſociety or company,</hi> who excelleth in wealth, and for that cauſe is ſelected and choſen aboue the reſt to rule over others. But the hebrew text hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> your teachers and inſtructers. And therefore howſoever it may include the temporall gouernours, yet is it chiefly and primarily to bee vnderſtood of ſpirituall. For the hebrew by the iudgement of divers graue autors, is the true vernacle and authentique copie of this epiſtle. And where it followeth: <hi>For they watch for your ſoules;</hi> doth more properly belong to the eccleſiaſticall then ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill gouernors. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath two ſignifications to giue eare, or bee perſuaded vnto, and to obey. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Zenop. <hi>verbis perſuadeor,</hi> to be perſuaded by words, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>legi obſequens, Plato,</hi> to be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to laws. So the hebrew word here vſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is both to giue eare, and to obey; as they that are but meanely read in the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew doe eaſily knowe. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth, to yeeld vnto or ſubmit your ſelues vnto, or be ruled by. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iliad. a. Si tibi omni in re morem geram. &amp; Eurip <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nil dans loci ſenectuti.</hi> The he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> humble your ſelues vnder their hands, ſubmit your ſelues vnto them, yeeld vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vnto the voice of your teachers, follow their inſtructions and admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, obey the commandements conſtitutions and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, of them or other your gouernors, &amp; if you chance to bee diſobedient in ſome things, ſhewe not your ſelues ſtubborne or obſtinate, but ſubmit your ſelues vnto them, and ſuppoſe they bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>rigidi moroſi</hi> auſtere, ſevere or otherwiſe faulty, beare with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſubmit your ſelues
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15919:4"/> to their autority as vnto Gods ſubſtitutes. This being the ſumme and meaning. The parts are two, Firſt an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or rather a commandement vnto inferiors, to bee obedient vnto thoſe that bee in authoritie over them, to inſtruct and gouerne them. Secondly reaſons to inforce obedience vnto this commandement, The firſt reaſon is drawne from the office and dignitie of the perſon vnto whome obedience is to bee giuen, they are ſuch ouerſeers as watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt bee readie to giue an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ſecond <hi>ab honeſto,</hi> it were great ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude by our diſobedience to moue them to performe this charge with griefe of minde, and not rather with ioy and comfort. The third fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the effect; for this in the end wil be vnprofitable for you, the worſt wil be yours. Of theſe in order as they lie.</p>
            <p>But firſt before I come to handle the particulers, let this one thing not impertinently be remembred in the generall. That God hath made a difference of degrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his people, even from the beginning, and ſtil doth &amp; muſt continue amongſt Chriſtians vnder the Goſpell. where there hath beene and alwaies and now is, ſuperiors and inferiors, ſome to rule and ſome to be ruled. And this appeareth in the very frame of nature; for in the order of the vniuerſall, all creatures are ſubordinate vnto their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors vntill they come to the higheſt ſupreame power. Among the elements the earth is vnder the water, the water the aire, the aire the element of fire, and that to the orbe of the moone, &amp; every planet with their orbes one vnder another, and all the celeſtiall bodies differ one from another in glorie and dignitie, which order, the ſuperior bodies by their influences, and the elements by their alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, do not only bring perfection vnto the whole
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15919:5"/> but is the preſervation of the whole. So in the heauenly company and Church, there are Arch-angels, Angels, principalities, powers, dominions, thrones, cherubins &amp; ſeraphins. S. Hierom in his ſecond booke againſt Iovini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an proueth both out of divers places of the Goſpel, &amp; out of many places of the old Teſtament this point at large &amp; how that in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there ſhal be differences of the degrees of glory. And out of the epiſtles of S. Paul in the ſimilitude of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of a mans body, ſome parts are more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then other there is the head aboue the foot, the eie more honorable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the legge, &amp;c. For, ſaith he, ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are ſo neceſſary as we cannot liue without them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch as though they bee cut off &amp; we maymed, yet may we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue life. And the Philoſopher to proue this principle from the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of nature, ſheweth; that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is by nature made to gouerne the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the wiſe, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; the mighty, to gouerne the fooliſh, the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the baſe and the weake, the father the children, and the maſter the ſervants. Now take away this order, and the frame of nature would goe to ruine, to the former confuſed chaos, take away this order, and humane ſocietie cannot be maintained, nay without this the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of Saints cannot be maintained. Againſt the Anabaptiſts and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts who would ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue all men equall and all things in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Yet Chriſt bid giue to Caeſar thoſe things which were Caeſars, and S. Paul bids every ſoule to be ſubiect to the higher powers for there is no power but of God, and hee calleth them Gods Miniſters, &amp; yet at that time there was no chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrate. This being granted, yet here ſome make queſtion, whether there be any ſuperioritie or inferioritie amongſt the miniſters of the Goſpell, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be ſubiection and obedience due to bee giuen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15919:5"/> of the one to the other. In the Apoſtles time it is plaine there were Prophets, and Apoſtles, Paſtors, Teachers, Prieſts or Elders, Deacons, Biſhops, Evangeliſts, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and divers others. In the ages ſucceeding the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the general conſent of al antiquitie &amp; the Churches of God eaſterne and weaſterne in all ages hitherto haue kept a difference of degrees in the Church, ſome beſides laboring in the word of God to rule and gouerne, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that alſo labour in the worde and are ſubiect and to be gouerned by others. S. Hierom, in his ſecond booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Jouinian, proueth that both in the Goſpell as well as in the law it is hath and muſt be ſo, for ſaith he,<note place="margin">Yet perhaps S. Hieron, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this point more ſparing becauſe he ſhould haue beene elected Biſhop of Rome, and by reaſon of his a mula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe.</note> 
               <hi>ſine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa eſt diuerſitas nominum ſi non ſit diuerſitas meritoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And in his commentarie vpon the 19. Chapter of Eſay, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fiue orders in the Church, Biſhops, Prieſts, Deacons, Beleeuers, and thoſe that were yet catechiſed, and not admitted to the participation of the ſacraments. In his epiſtle <hi>ad Ruſticum Monachum</hi> he ſaith, <hi>ſinguli eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum Epiſcopi, ſinguli archipreſbyteri, ſinguli archidiaconi, &amp; omnis ordo eccleſiaſticus ſuis rectoribus nititur;</hi> mentioning Biſhops, and Prieſts that had alſo autoritie of gouerning, and Archdeacons. But in his comment on the 6. of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, he ſaith that Biſhops Prieſts and every Eccleſiaſticall order ought to feed the flock of Chriſt; and in this diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation there is no difference, but as it pleaſeth God to giue diverſitie of gifts, and bleſſing to the outward meanes by the inward working of the ſpirit. And further in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie vpon the epiſtle of S. Paul to Titus, he ſheweth that the occaſion of the difference in autority of Prieſts, or Elders, and Biſhops, was by reaſon of ſciſmes and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, which even in the Apoſtles time then began to riſe: which might ſeeme to haue beene an ordinance then in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15919:6"/> force. In another place hee ſaith that vnleſſe this order were, we ſhould haue as many miniſters, ſo many ſciſmes. In all S. Auguſtines workes and al the fathers before him, they all mention a difference betweene <hi>Preſbyterum</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopum</hi> both in autoritie and dignitie. Bucer in his booke <hi>de animarum cura officio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eccleſiaſtici paſtoris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. etiam S. Hier. in ep ſtola Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rio cum anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi.</note> 
               <hi>p. 280. excuſ. Baſiliae. anno. 77.</hi> commenteth thus vpon S. Hierom: It is not credible that this parity betweene <hi>Epiſcopum</hi> and <hi>Preſbyterum</hi> continued long in any one Church, neither was it generally at any time obſerued in all Churches, for even from the times of the Apoſtles, ſome one Prieſt or elder was choſen amongſt the reſt, which ſhould be in authoritie aboue the reſt; as a guid and gouernor to rule all the reſt, as he proueth out of Act. 15. that S. Iames was Biſhop of Hieruſalem, &amp;c. And that this ordination of Biſhops was perpetually obſerued in all Churches, may be gathered by all eccleſiaſticall hiſtories and ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as Tertullian, Cyprian, Irenaeus, Euſebius &amp;c. The neceſſity hereof he amplifieth with reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnanſwerable. To this ſame purpoſe read the Kings Maieſties Apologie p. 45. 46 at ful. And in al the oecumenical counſels &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Synodes which were from time to time kept for the maintenance of vnity &amp; repreſſing of hereſie; Who were there to diſcuſſe, determine &amp; order matters in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, to ſet down the confeſſion of faith for vnitie, to make ordinances and conſtitutions wherevnto miniſters and people were ſubiect, were they inferior miniſters or Biſhops? In all this time there was no queſtion, whether the Church ought to be gouerned by Biſhops and other miniſters of inferior autoritie and yet ſuperior to others. If amongſt vs this order of gouernment were not, both miniſters and miniſtery would grow into contempt, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15919:6"/> ſuch anarchie here would be the overthrow of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and Church of God amongſt vs. Thus much for the generall.</p>
            <p>Now to ſpeake of the particuler obedience, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in two things: firſt in the obedience to the word of God preached, by him that watcheth for the ſoule. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of yeelding obedience vnto the autoritie of ſuch miniſters, as are in preheminence, as alſo in obeying their lawes, conſtitutions and ordinances. And firſt touching obedience vnto the word, where we are to conſider, that vnleſſe we reverence the man that preacheth the word, at leaſt for his calling and office ſake, the worde preached by him ſhall be to ſmale effect. Which Saint Paul knew well when <hi>(1 Cor. 4.1.)</hi> he ſaith <hi>let a man eſteeme of vs as the miniſters of God, and diſpenſers of his miſteries.</hi> And Gal. 4.14.15. he glorieth, that the Galatians receiued him as an Angel, yea as Chriſt himſelfe, and that their loue to him was ſuch, that if it had beene poſſible they would haue pulled out their very eies to haue done him good; &amp; this their reſpect of him was a glory and renowne vnto them. Our Saviour Chriſt complaineth, that the baſe eſteeme that his country-men had of him was the occaſion why he preached little, wroght few miracles, and his comming was ſo little availeable to them. This made S. Paul ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to right his reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the practiſes of the falſe apoſtles, who in many places ſtandeth much both in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the autoritie of his Apoſtleſhip, and alſo in exalting of his gifts, &amp; declaring the integritie of his converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Chriſt to teach the honor due vnto his miniſters, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon them his perſon and ſaith <hi>(Mat. 10)</hi> that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement and reſpect given vnto them, hee account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth done vnto himſelfe. We read that the Prophets were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15919:7"/> ſometimes called me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, ſometimes Prophets of the Lord, and even Kings called them fathers. 2. King. 6.21. In like manner S. Paul in divers places calleth his auditors his ſonnes and himſelfe their father, ſhewing that as hee loued them as his naturall ſonnes, ſo ought they much more to honour him as their father.<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potianum eſto ſubiectus Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici tuo &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam animae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem ſuſpice.</note> In the Revelation miniſters are called Angels, a high title of honor. 1: Tim. 5.17: The Apoſtle teacheth that <hi>thoſe elders that rule well are worthy of double honour,</hi> the meaneſt then are worthy of honor, becauſe they are more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues, they are the Embaſſadors of Chriſt. 2. Cor. 1.14. <hi>pro Chriſto legatione fungimur.</hi> Now doe but conſider this, the place and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they do ſuſtaine, that Gods autority doth ſhine in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> emineently, and we ſhal eaſily conclude, that to deny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the honor and reſpect due vnto their office and place, is to clip Gods coine, is treaſon againſt God himſelfe. In the 5. commandement, the yeelding of a due honor hath the promiſe of a bleſſed long life,<note place="margin">Vid. Bueer in lib. de ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne miniſtrorum eccleſia circa i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitium.</note> the contrary muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cure a wretched life and a curſed death, in the 2 King: 2.24: verſe. when certaine children mocked Elizeus, God curſed them, and ſent a ſhee beare out of a wood adioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which devoured 42 of them. Therefore ſeeing we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our lawier that watcheth for our goods, and our Phiſition for the health of our bodies, much more ought their feete ſeeme beautifull vnto vs, that watch for our ſoules, that bring vs the glad tidings of ſalvation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The conſideration of this will manifeſt vnto vs the wicked frowardnes of ſuch, as without all feare of God or reſpect of common civilitie (howſoeuer they will ſeeme to doe it in zeale of religion) wil ſpeake evil of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in authoritie, &amp; eſpecially of the miniſters from the higheſt to the loweſt, they wil beſpurtle al with one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15919:7"/> blot or other though they bee never ſo ſober, learned, reverend, godly or graue, yet al muſt be either falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, antichriſtian prelats, timeſervers, idle or evill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yea though they preach oft, if they preach not twice on the ſunday, they muſt bee damned creatures, dumb dogges, and what not if they bee not of their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: for to frame lies, to raiſe ſlaunders, to backbite or any waies to impeach, any that are conformable to the gouernement of the Church, they account it religion, and he the moſt forward, that herein ſheweth himſelfe moſt impudent: And this is ſo common a vice annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the inbred-pride of faction, that few of them that are refractorie to the gouernement eſtabliſhed, are free from: but Saint James tels them, they ſeeme to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bee religeous but their ill gouerned tongue ſhewes their religion is vaine.</p>
               <p>Another ſort there are, that eſteeme baſely of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as they be miniſters; who though their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and contempt of God be herein farre greater, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other; yet are they herein the leſſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous, becauſe they maske not in the cloke of religion, but manifeſt their prophane hearts to all men, yet it were meete that ſuch groſſe contempt ſhould not eſcape vnpuniſhed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>But the former ſort obiect and ſay, they giue honor to the miniſterie and the miniſters, though they eſteeme of ſome and not of others, I ſhould ſay, more then others; they only denie it to them that are not lawfull miniſters, which haue not a lawfull outward calling, or want the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling which is gifts, aptneſſe to teach.</p>
            <p>For the lawfulnes of the outward calling of our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, it was not called into queſtion either by Bucer, Pet. Martyr, or any of our worthy champions at the time of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15919:8"/> the reſtoring of the Goſpell, nor euer ſince, by any godly learned, nor by any other proteſtant Church: amongſt all which, the glorie of our Church ſhineth in brightnes as the moone amongſt the ſtarres; yet if there bee any that herein make ſcruple let him reade S. Auguſtine and other learned and ancient fathers againſt the Donatiſts, which ſerueth for ful confutation of the ſame ſect renued in our daies vnder other names.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond obiection, that the miniſter happily is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> apt to teach, and therefore no lawfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, nor worthy of the honour of a miniſter. Wee wiſh with Moſes and I would to God that all our miniſters in England, were good preachers, yet wee knowe that in all ages, there haue been ſome miniſters in the Church, who could preach and for ſloth would not, and ſome others that for want of gifts could not, and yet were ever held for lawfull miniſters.</p>
            <p>In the eſtabliſhing of the Goſpell after the aboliſhing of Popery, there was not a ſufficient number of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and therefore there were many godly men, choſen by godly Biſhops &amp; Martyres, into the miniſtery, that ſhould read the Scriptures and praiers of the Church, catechiſe according to a forme preſcribed, read homilies, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſacraments, &amp; haue the help of preachers month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or quarterly, or as oft as they could bee had. And ſince then, there are very many places, where the ſtipend is not ſufficient to maintaine a preacher, and are of neceſſity ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with an vnpreaching miniſter; And yet wee doubt not, but the people vnder them, may performe accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice to God, in hearing reverently the word read, in ioining with him in publike prayers of the Church, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diligent care to the homilies and ſermons which he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15919:8"/> readeth, receiueth the ſacraments, and heare ſermons ſo oft as they can haue them, and bee in as good ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as ſome people, that haue diuers ſermons made by extempory men, which ſtand vpon the preſent aſſiſtance of the ſpirit, <hi>dabitur in illa hora,</hi> and preach their own idle humors. <hi>S. Auguſt. lib. 4. cap. 8. de doctrina chriſtiana.</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that there were in the Church in his time, ſome mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which had not the gift of preaching, of whome hee made no queſtion but that they were lawfull miniſters, &amp; he approueth their reading of homilies or pronouncing of other mens ſermons to the better edifying and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of their people. Theſe are his words. <hi>Sunt ſane qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, qui bene pronunciare poſſunt, quid autem pronuncient excogitare non poſſunt; quod ſi ab alijs ſumant eloquenter ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſcriptum, memoriae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> commendent at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad populum proferant, ſi eam perſonam gerunt, non improbè faciunt.</hi> And by your leaue, a great parte of our curious preachers, which envie ſo much againſt reading of homilies, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure that a learned man ſhould vſe the helpe of his owne notes in the pulpit, (becauſe they themſelues can preach little worth noting) which will ſeeme to preach all out of the Bible and their owne meditations, yet will they preach other mens ſermons, printed and written, and ſtudy little elſe; and howſoeuer they knowe themſelues to be vnlearned, yet doe they account of themſelues, and will be accounted more then ordinary preachers. I would haue them to deny miniſters that haue not the gifts to make a ſufficient ſermon themſelues, to bee lawfull mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, &amp; then we ſhould haue a great many of their prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers in the ſame ſtate. Let it bee proued that aptneſſe to make &amp; preach ſermons of themſelues is the forme &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a miniſter, which cannot bee gathered out of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15919:9"/> Paul, though queſtionleſſe it is the principall qualitie in any miniſter. Againe if ſuch ſhalbe denied to be miniſters (the congregations vnder them may as well be denied to be viſible members of the Church of God) then muſt the ſacraments adminiſtred by them, bee denied to bee ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but ſo doth no proteſtant Church eſteeme of our miniſters and congregations, nor any of any ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: S. Auguſtine <hi>Contra Parmentanum Donatiſtam, &amp; contra Creſconium grammaticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; contra Petilianum,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the dignitie of the ſacraments dependeth not of the worthineſſe of the miniſter, becauſe the ſacraments are Chriſts, and whoſoever the miniſter be that baptiſeth with water, it is hee that baptiſeth with the holy Ghoſt. To conclude this point the honor due vnto a miniſter,<note place="margin">Vnderſtanding that this doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine touching the reading of homilies by ſuch as are not of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient abilitie to frame ſermons, was offenſiuely taken as falſe &amp; erronius. Let ſuch offenſiue men know, that herein I ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that which M. Bucer in his cenſure vpon our booke of common pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er hath written for the ſubſtance in his 7 chapter whither I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the equall reader eſpec. As for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets let them now bite him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after many yeeres buried, was burned for deſpite borne vnto his doct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> is not to be denied vnto him, that hath not gifts of himſelfe ſufficient to make ſermons, ſeeing that this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he cannot be denied to be a lawfull miniſter, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thoſe that haue greater gifts are worthy of double honour.</p>
            <p>Yet herein the ſlackneſſe of ſome of the gouernors of our Church cannot be excuſed, for there are many, that if they were vrged and inioined, haue ſufficiencie both of learning and vtterance, but their careleſneſſe and idlenes is ſuch, that vnleſſe they bee compelled they will take no pains. There are others that with good directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; helps of their able neighbouring miniſters, would in ſhort time be brought vnto a reaſonable ſufficiencie in preaching; as I haue knowne the experience of many in divers places. Now for the reſt, which are not able of themſelues to frame ſermons, they might be enioined to the catechiſing which is appointed by autoritie, and to read homilies which are ſet forth and enioined, and to procure their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15919:9"/> weekely or monthly ſermons at the leaſt, according to the iniunctions and Canons. And ſeeing it hath beene a fault of ſome particuler gouernors (and not the fault of the gouernment, which commandeth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary) to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ſuch inſufficient men, in places where ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t main tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is for able preachers, it were to be wiſhed that for the time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, they would admit none into ſuch places but preachers. And this evil was wiſely foreſeen &amp; thought very neceſſarie to be redreſſed, when as by our eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lawes they ought to be graduats and of a good age, &amp; and not meere grammer ſchollers, nor youths, which are to be admitted into the miniſtery. Moreouer our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of our Churches ſhould doe a good and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſervice, to take a ſure ſurvey of thoſe that are preachers what their ſufficiency is, for many out of their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pride, or to avoid the name of a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>preacher, though they haue no learning nor any competent vnderſtanding in the ſcriptures, will take vpon them to preach very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, yea ſome of them twice or thrice a weeke, and God knowes, knowe not how nor what they preach, to the great diſhonor of God and reproach of preachers, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the preaching of the word in contempt, and to bee ieſted at. Theſe vnpreaching preachers doe more harme in the Church and more hinder the obedience vnto the Goſpel, then any one thing, theſe ought to bee forbidden to preach till they bee better inſtructed. Laſtly, ſeeing the calling of miniſters is to bee reverenced; they are to admoniſh the miniſters, generally and particularly, that by their pietie, integritie, diligence and charitie, they would force men to yeeld that reverence and obedience as they are bound vnto and as becommeth them.</p>
            <p>Now for the reverence and obedience vnto the word
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15919:10"/> of God preached by the miniſter. For as the reverent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of the miniſtery &amp; miniſters, is a great cauſe that the people receiue the word of God with more alacrity and to their greater profit: So the meſſage which they bring. i. the word of God, addeth autority and honour to the miniſter, and cauſeth obedience to be yeelded vnto it. For vnles we be perſwaded, that they are Gods miniſters, and that the word which they deliver, is Gods word, wee ſhall neither profit by it, nor yeeld obedience vnto it, nay it will bee a fauor of death vnto death vnto vs, when wee ſhall be guilty of taking Gods name in vaine, and refuſe the word of reconciliation &amp; meanes of ſalvation offred. S. Paul 1. Theſſ. 2.13. reioiceth that the Theſſalonians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the word preached, <hi>not as the word of man, but as it is indeed the word of God.</hi> &amp; 2. Cor. 4.7. <hi>we haue this treaſure in earthen veſſels, that the excellency of the vertue thereof might be of God and not of ourſelues.</hi> And this is not only in the Prophets and Apoſtles who were extraordinary men directed in ſpeciall manner by the holy Ghoſt; but of all ordinary miniſters in the Church, that ſo long as they ſpeak the truth of God according to the Scriptures, &amp; draw ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, &amp; apply it to our vſe, this word ſo preached, is to be eſteemed as the word of God, and ſo to be reverenced and obeyed. And they that ſhal o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe eſteeme of it, ſhalbe guilty of taking Gods name in vaine. For in old time God revealed his wil, by dreames, viſions and ſometimes by his owne voice from heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet after hee had ordained an ordinary miniſtery, hee made knowne his will vnto the people by them. In the 20. of Exod. ver. 19. After the law was delivered with thunder &amp; lightnings and the noyze of trumpets, and the ſmoaking of the mountaine, the people were ſore affraide, and made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15919:10"/> requeſt vnto Moſes, that they might not heare God ſpeak, but that Moſes might be for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God, &amp; deliver Gods will to them. In this ordinance of God, that his Miniſters ſhould declare his will vnto the people; firſt he declareth his good will toward vs, when he taketh out of men them that ſhal do his meſſage in the world, that ſhalbe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his ſecret will, that ſhal repreſent his owne perſon. And ſo by experience he proveth, that it is not vaine that commonly hee calleth vs his temples, when out of the mouthes of men as out of his ſanctuarie hee giveth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to men. Secondly, this is the beſt and moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table exerciſe to humility, when hee accuſtometh vs to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his word, howſoever it be preached by men like vnto vs, yea ſometimes our inferiors in dignity. Thirdly, there was nothing fitter for the cheriſhing of mutuall charitie then that men ſhould bee bound togither with this bond, when one is made paſtor to teach the reſt, and the people are commanded to be ſchollers of the ſame ſchoole, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all one doctrine at one mouth. Theſe points Calvin handleth ſo largely and ſo pithily that I referre them that would be farther ſatisfied, vnto his fourth booke of Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and third chapter.</p>
            <p>But here ariſe two maine doubts, the one touching the doctrine, the ſecond touching the life of the Miniſter. Firſt as concerning the doctrine; it ſeemeth that here is great danger, if we ſhall take all for true Prophets, and all that is delivered for Gods word. For we read 1. King. 18.26. and 1. King. 22.6. and many other places, that their were falſe prophets, and therefore Deut. 18.20.21. the Lord is faine to teach them how, to know the true Prophet from the falſe, whether they ſpeake his word or their owne.</p>
            <p>Touching Prophets their calling was immediate and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15919:11"/> extraordinary, there was no ſuch queſtion of Levits or Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> Our Saviour Chriſt in the goſpell Mat. 7.15. bids his diſciples to beware of falſe Prophets: and S. Paule, and S. Jude, make mention of falſe teachers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp: </seg>
               </label> In our Saviour Chriſts time, the extraordinary calling of Prophets was not altogither ceaſed. And the Apoſtle ſpake not of ordinary Miniſters, but of ſuch as went about like Apoſtles or Evangeliſts, and ſuch as without any ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led place or ordinary calling, went from place to place to ſowe hereſies, ſome of which denied Chriſt the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome taught doctrines of devils and damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. If they had meant ordinary miniſters in an eſtabliſhed Church, they would haue eaſily told them a redreſſe, by ordinary proceeding either to reclaime or depoſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> Yet further it is obiected. 1. Ioh. 4. we are commanded to try the ſpirits whether they be of God or no &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp: </seg>
               </label> Indeed many herevpon ignorantly &amp; preſumptuouſly haue and doe aſſume vnto themſelues a power and liberty to dieue into the ſecrets of God, and to cenſure ſome to be miniſters of God and ſent by him, ſome to bee no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miniſters, but ſend themſelues; ſome this and that at their pleaſure: Whereas the Apoſtle giueth no ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but expoundeth himſelfe in the wordes following, that he that denieth the Lord Ieſus to be come in the fleſh is not of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> But how if vpon the right foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they build wood hay, ſtubble, inſteed of gold, ſiluer and precious ſtones?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp: </seg>
               </label> God ſuffereth ſuch ſometimes 1 To ſtirre vp our care and attention, to teach vs to doe as the noble Bereans did Act. 17.11. Secondly to try vs (as Deut. 13.3.) whether we will bee carried away with every blaſt of falſe doctrine.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15919:11"/> Thirdly, to try the miniſters humilitie, whether he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his error when he is convinced, and reforme it, as <hi>S. Auguſtine de catechizandis rudibus</hi> declareth. <hi>Quod ſi humanae infirmitatis intentio, etiam ab ipſa rerum veritate errauer it, ne forte accidat vt hinc offendatur auditor. Non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liunde nobis debet videri accidiſſe, niſi quia Deus experiri nos voluit, vtrum cum mentis placiditate corrigamur; ne in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſione noſtri erroris, maiori praecipitemur errori.</hi> Fourthly to teach the miniſter not to truſt to his wit or preſent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, but by ſtudie, reading, meditation &amp; prayer prepare himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> But many preach much out of humane writers &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, therefore their ſermons are not to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as the word of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp: </seg>
               </label> If their ſayings alleadged by the preacher, be agreeable to the word of God and fitly applied, they are to be receiued as the word; becauſe if it bee truth, it is of him that is the truth the way and the life. Heare what Saint Auguſtin, in <hi>lib. 2. de doctrina chriſtiana cap. 40.</hi> ſaith of this point: <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophietiam qui vocantur, ſi qua forte vera &amp; fidei noſtrae accommoda dixerunt, non ſolum formidanda non ſunt, ſed ab ijs etiam tanquam iniuſtis poſſeſſoribus in vſum noſtrum ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicanda &amp;c.</hi> The heathen Philoſophers (ſaith hee) thoſe things which they haue ſpoken truely, and agreeable to our faith, we ought to be ſo farre of from being afraid of it, as that we are to challenge it from them as from vniuſt poſſeſſors to our owne vſe, as the Iſraelites did the veſſels, iewels and rayment, which they borrowed from the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians &amp;c. To the ſame purpoſe S. Hierom.<note place="margin">Vid etiam S. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eron Tom. 2 pag 326 Baſu-edit. epiſt magno ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tori Romano hanc quaeſt. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pioſe diſputante</note> And now to conclude this point alſo. If thou ſuſpect that thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the preacher preach that which is neither the worde of God nor agreeable vnto it, carry the point to be diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15919:12"/> by ſome miniſters that be in autority (if he himſelfe do not ſatiſfy thee) and let the ſpirit of the Prophets bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto the Prophets, and if it proue to bee an error, hee may either confeſſe his fault and renounce his error, or elſe til ſuch time be reſtrained. In the meane time, vnleſſe thou canſt proue by this meanes, the doctrine deliuered falſe, thou art bound to reverence it, to receiue it, &amp; to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, as the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> The ſecond maine obiection is the life of the miniſter, becauſe God ſometimes ſuffereth, ſome covetous Iudaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſome laſciuious ſonnes of Elie, ſome prophane Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures to be in the miniſterie, they thinke there is no reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due vnto them as they are miniſters of God, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto the word delivered by them, as vnto the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> This indeed is a great ſtumbling blocke which hath and doth cauſe many to fall And it were to bee wiſhed that by the cenſures of the church ſuch offences were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved either by reclaiming the offendors and bringing them into order, or els by ſuſpending them from their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vntill they amend: ſeeing as Hophne &amp; Phineas they make the Lords ſacrifices to be abhorred. Yet the Lorde ſuffreth ſuch to trie vs whether we wil hereat take offence and refuſe the precious pearle offered vnto vs becauſe it is brought vnto vs in an vncleane boxe. To meete with this evill our Saviour himſelfe hath given vs a leſſon, Mat. 23. <hi>The Scribes and Phareſies ſit in Moſes chaire, all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which they ſhall command you to obſerue, obſerue and do ye, but according to their workes do ye not, for they ſay and do not.</hi> S. Auguſtine in his 46. tract vpon S. Iohn writeth thus, <hi>Habet ovile domini praepoſitos, &amp; filios, &amp; mercenarios. Sed &amp; mercenarij etiam neceſſarij ſunt: multi quippe in eccleſia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15919:12"/> terren a ſectantes, Chriſtum tamen praedicant, &amp; per eos vox Chriſti auditur, &amp; ſequuntur oves non mercenarium, ſed vocem paſtoris per mercenarium. Sede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do enim cathedra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſi, legem Dei docent, ergo per illos Deus docet, &amp;c.</hi> The ſheepfold of Chriſt hath ſet over it, ſonnes &amp; hirelings. And yet the hirelings alſo are neceſſary, for there are manie in the church, which follow after worldly commodities and yet preach Chriſt, and by them is the voice of Chriſt heard; &amp; the ſheepe followe not the hireling but the voice of the ſheepheard by the hireling, for ſitting in Moſes chaire, they teach the law of God, therefore by them God teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And he alleadgeth S. Paul Phil. 1.15. ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e preach Chriſt of envy and contention, &amp; ſome of a willing minde, ſome of deſpight, thinking to adde affliction to his bonds, but howſoeuer, hee was glad that Chriſt was preached, and Phil 2.21. &amp;c. <hi>multis ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> proſunt dicendo quae non faciunt, ſed longe pluribus prodeſſent faciendo quae dicunt,</hi> they doe much good vnto many in ſaying that which they do not, but much more ſhould they do by doing that which they ſay. And in his ſecond booke <hi>contra Creſconium Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum,</hi> he anſwereth an obiection made by the Donatiſts out of the 50. Pſalme. <hi>What haſt thou to doe to preach my lawes, &amp;c.</hi> He expoundeth it thus, <hi>fruſtra hoc fit quantum ad te attinet, non tibi prodeſt, hoc tibi ad iudicium damnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non ad meritum ſalutis valebit.</hi> In vaine thou doeſt it as concerning thy ſelfe, this ſhall availe thee nothing, this ſhall not bee any meanes to ſaue thee, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee: but they that ſhall heare the worde at ſuch a mans mouth, beleue it and obey it, though he be damned, yet they ſhall be ſaued, becauſe they followed the counſell of our Saviour Chriſt Mat. 23. that which they ſay doe, but after their workes doe not, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15919:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> They that are evill men, and vnſanctified, cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert ſoules?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
               </label> Some I knowe, and thoſe of the preciſeſt ſort both of miniſters, and people haue held, that a formaliſt (for ſo they tearme al thoſe that in the feare of God &amp; obedience vnto the Prince conforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnto the laws preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) cannot convert ſoules, though he be never ſo learned or vpright in his converſation: they haue that gift them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>S. Auguſtin contra epiſt. Parmeniani lib. 2. cap. 11. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales homines non poſſe ſpiritales filios procreare. Ioh. 3. quod natum eſt ex carne caro eſt, quod natum ex ſpiritu ſpiritus eſt.</hi> Carnall men cannot beget ſpirituall children, becauſe the Evangeliſt ſaith, that which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Quaſi nos dicamus per ſeipſum quemlibet hominem ſpirita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les filios generare, &amp; non pro Evangelium in cuius praedicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſpiritus ſanctus operatur. 1. Cor. 4. ego vos genui per Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium, Euangelium autem fur quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Iudas ſine detrimento fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium praedicauit.</hi> As if ſo be we may ſay, that any man of himſelfe can beget ſpirituall children, and not by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, in the preaching whereof the holy Ghoſt worketh. As S. Paul ſaith 1. Cor. 4. I haue begotten you by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the theefe Iudas preached the Goſpell, without any detriment to the faithfull.</p>
            <p>By this that hath been ſaid in anſwere vnto the ſecond obiection, here ariſeth this concluſion. That evil and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, being miniſters of the Goſpell, are to bee heard. 2. That the word of God preached by them is to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and obeyed as Gods word, and may bee profitable to our ſaluation. 3. That they notwithſtanding are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced for the calling &amp; place ſake. And thus much for the firſt branch of obedience in hearing.</p>
            <p>Now for obedience vnto eccleſiaſticall lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15919:13"/> D. H. Zanchie, ſheweth, how that many not knowing the difference betweene humane traditions and eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions, brand them both with one blacke marke. The neceſſitie of theſe he proueth at large by vnanſwerable arguments, to bee ſuch, as without the which, concord peace and vnitie, order nor decency can be obſerued, nor the Church of God conſiſt or be, nor any publike worſhip of God bee preſerued and maintained. Yet the neceſſity of theſe or thoſe in particuler, is not ſuch as that they are accounted neceſſary to ſalvation, or that of themſelues they bind the conſcience with a religious obſervation of them. So in the preface to the booke of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer, where reaſons are giuen of the aboliſhing of ſome ceremonies and the retaining of others, is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſelfe ſame thing, and that many of theſe in our Church, may vpon iuſt cauſes, which the Church &amp; ſtate ſhall thinke good, be changed or altered, &amp; therefore are not held equall in autority to the word of God. And we knowe there is as great diverſitie in the mindes of men, as is in their viſages, &amp; therefore if ſome orders ſhould not be ſet down, but that every man ſhould be left to his own liberty, we ſhould haue ſo many ſeuerall congregations, ſo many diuers religions. We ſee the varietie of opinions touching the geſture in receiuing the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though there be order ſet downe for the receiuing of it kneeling. Some hold it vnlawfull to kneele, and deeme that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſtanding is the beſt way, as here in this place. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers condemne kneeling as Popiſh and idolatrous, and hold ſtanding as Iewiſh as the other Popiſh, and therefore ſay that Chriſts example in this muſt bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs a lawe and rule from which wee may not varie: hee received it ſitting, and therfore any other geſture vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15919:14"/> Thus wee ſee, if in this and other things, every man were left to his owne liberty, what an endleſſe worke there would be, there would be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord in nothing but in diverſities and diſagreements. The vſe and ende of theſe rites (as D. Zanchie ſaith) are firſt that they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a reverence vnto the holy things; and that by ſuch helpes we may be ſtirred vp vnto godlines, &amp; by a ſtreight hand be led vnto Chriſt. The ſecond end, That modeſty &amp; gravity, which in all other actions ought to bee regarded, may herein chiefly appeare. Afterwards he proveth that eccleſiaſtical traditions and conſtitutions, are not meerely humane but divine, good, true, holy, and pleaſing to God, becauſe they are ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the church, which is guided by the ſpirit of God which is truth. For the particulers they are partly humane, and partly divine; divine becauſe they are a part of that order and decorum, that God hath commanded in generall, leaving the particulers to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the church to bee framed according to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule.</p>
            <p>Now as there muſt of neceſſitie be a vniforme order in theſe things preſcribed: ſo alſo is it no leſſe neceſſary to ſee vniformity in the obſervance of theſe orders. For they are made to mainetaine and preſerue vnity, and therefore ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to be obſerved in thoſe places where they are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. And if any inferior governors in the church (who are to ſee vniforme orders to be obſerved) will ſee ſome obſerved and ſome others wilfully to be broken: It were in my opinion much better for them to be meanes vnto ſuperior autority, that thoſe orders which they thinke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit were altered; then that this liberty of diverſity ſhoulde be given, which breeds ſo great ſcandals. For I knowe by manifold experience, the danger that this diverſity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15919:14"/> orders bringeth. Some poore ſoules haue and doe ſtand amazed, whileſt they ſee in one pariſh one forme of praiers and adminiſtring the ſacraments, and another in the next pariſh. They thinke theſe are divers religions and doubt what they may follow. Herevpon it commeth to paſſe that ſome fall to Popery, ſome to Atheiſme, &amp; ſome to other hereſies &amp; ſchiſmes. Theſe inconveniences were wiſely foreſeene, in the eſtabliſhing of an act in Parlament for vniformity. And if political lawes of heathen princes, be to be obſerved for conſcience ſake (ſo that they enioine not diſobedience to God) much more theſe that are for mainetenance of concord, order and decencie in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. <hi>Aug. epiſt. 166. Hoc iubent imperatores quod iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet &amp; Chriſtus, quia cum bonum iubent, per illos non iubet niſi Chriſtus.</hi> That which kings commande, that Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, becauſe when as they commande that which is good, Chriſt commandeth by them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> But many of our lawes ordinances and conſtitutions, ſay ſome, are vnlawful: Therefore not to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> Bucer being written vnto by D. Cranmer then Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Canterbury (and alſo by B. Hooper, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in his booke <hi>de ſacris veſtibus</hi>) Touching the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theſe matters which are now made queſtion of by divers, writeth his cenſure at large vpon our booke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier liturgie and ceremonies. Now he ſaith, that when firſt he came into this land, he made doubt whether he might ioine with our church as with a church of God, things were ſo farre out of order; but when hee looked more ſeriouſly into the matter, he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the fault was in the manners of the men and for want of the execution of the wholeſome orders preſcribed, and not in the lawes and ordinances preſcribed themſelues: after hee doubteth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15919:15"/> not to avouch that touching our lawes,<note place="margin">Bucer ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our book of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> orders and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline eſtabliſhed, he found not any thing, that was not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, or by neceſſary conſequence, drawne out of the word of God, howſoever he wiſhed that ſome things that troubled the conſciences of ſome men, were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for their ſakes that tooke offence; which hee ſheweth in particuler. Peter Martyr in his Epiſtles ſeemeth to bee of the ſame iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> Others thinke that all or the moſt of our ceremonies are lawfull in themſelues, but the impoſing a neceſſitie in obſerving of them, deſtroieth Chriſtian liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> That is, they were lawfull if they were not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. Indeed vpon this conceipt, ſome do ſtrongly and ſtrangly hold, that the king may not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande them to weare their ordinary apparell of this or that faſhion, much leſſe any to be vſed in the Church, for they muſt ſtande vpon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty. A ſtrange principle of obedience, and like to breed loialty in the ſubiects towards their Prince. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile vnto what this humor woulde growe, if it were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> Againe, ſome think they ought not to yeeld obedience to theſe orders of the church, becauſe they are not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but ſtand in doubt, and whatſoever is not of faith but is done doubtingly, is a ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> It is much better to obey doubtingly, then to diſobey doubtingly: but me thinkes they ſhould reaſon thus. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am enioined to doe ſuch a thing, if I obey not the authoritie of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, I muſt needes ſin, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I can manifeſtly proue that; that which is comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded is vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> There are others that grant them lawful: but (ſay they) we cannot yeeld vnto them without offence, and ſcandall of Many.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15919:15"/>
            <p>Chriſt paid tribute Mat. 17.27. which he was not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto ſeeing he was free: yet nevertheleſſe hee did it for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding offence. Now theſe men in ſeeking to ſhun of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of I know not whom they imagine, will run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the wilful offence of the church &amp; whole ſtate, and raſhly breake the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord &amp; vnity of the Church. This is to ſtreine at a Gnat and ſwallow a Cammell. S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin writeth at large moſt divinely on this point. <hi>Epiſt. 118. ad Ianuarium.</hi> Thoſe things, ſaith hee, which we obſerue not by written autority, but by tradition, which are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved throughout the whole world, we muſt vnderſtand, that they are commanded and appointed by the Apoſtles themſelues, or els are decreed in lawfull councels whoſe authority in the Church is moſt wholeſome and holy. As that the paſſion, reſurrection, and aſcenſion of our Savior Chriſt, the comming of the holy Ghoſt, are celebrated &amp; ſolemnized yearely, &amp; whatſoever ſuch like is obſerved of the whole church generally. There are others which are different in ſeveral places &amp; countries, as that ſome faſt on the ſatterdaies, &amp; ſome do not, ſome receiue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> every day, ſome ſatterdaies &amp; ſondaies only, ſome on ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies only, &amp; ſome at ſet times. <hi>Totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc genus habet liberas obſervationes, nec eſt diſciplina ulla in his rebus melior gravi prudenti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viro, quam ut eo modo agat, quo agere viderit eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam adquamcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> forte devenerit. Quod enim ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra bonos mores iniungitur, indifferenter eſt habendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; pro eorum inter quos vivitur ſocietate, ſeruandum est.</hi> All things of this kinde are free to be obſerved as the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler churches ſhall thinke good; neither is there in theſe things any better rule to a graue &amp; prudent man, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he behaue himſelfe ſo as the church doth vnto which hee ſhall happyly come. For that which is enioined if it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15919:16"/> againſt faith nor manners, is to be held indifferent, &amp; ought to be obſerved according as they do in place where wee liue. Then he ſheweth that his mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnto him to Millain, ſhee found that the church there did not faſt on the ſatterdaies, &amp; ſhee began to be troubled and to doubt what ſhee might doe. Then ſaith he, for her ſake I went vnto S. Ambroſe and aſked his councell touching this matter: he anſwered me that hee could teach me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that thus he did himſelfe, and if he knewe better he would rather obſerue it. When as I thought that hee would haue yeelded me no other reaſon but his owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, he proceeded and ſaide vnto me, when I come to the church of Rome I faſt on the ſatterday, and when I am here I doe not, <hi>Sic etiam tu ad quam forte eccleſiam veneris eius morem ſerua, ſi cuiquam non vis eſſe ſcandalum nec quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam tibi.</hi> So thou alſo, vnto whatſoever church thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt, follow the orders thereof, if thou wouldeſt not ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize any, nor haue any to offend thee. When I had tolde this to my mother, ſhee was ſatisfied. <hi>Ego vero de hac ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia etiam at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> etiam cogitans, ita ſemper habui tanquam ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coelesti oraculo ſuſceperim: ſenſi enim ſaepe dolens &amp; gemens, multas infirmorum perturbationes fieri, per quorundam fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum contentioſam obſtinationem &amp; ſuperstitioſam timidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, qui in rebus huiuſmodi, quae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſcripturae ſanctae auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> univerſalis eccleſiae traditione, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vitae corrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vtilitate, ad certum poſſunt terminum pervenire, tantum quia ſubeſt qualiſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ratiocinatio cogitantis, aut quia in ſua patria ſic ipſe conſuevit, aut quia ibi vidit, ubi peregrinatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuam quo remotiorem à ſuis eo doctiorem putat, tam litigioſas excitant quaeſtiones, ut niſi quod ipſi faciunt nihil rectum exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimant.</hi> I often revolving in my minde this ſaying of S. Ambroſe, haue alwaies accompted of it, as if ſo be I had
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15919:16"/> received it by an oracle from heaven: For with ſorrow &amp; griefe I haue oftentimes found, that many weake ons haue beene ſore troubled, through the contentious obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and ſuperſtitious feare of certaine brethren: who in thoſe things, which neither by the autoritie of the holy ſcripture, nor by the generall tradition of the Church, nor for the vtilitie of amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life, can be brought to any certaine ende, only becauſe ſome make ſome curious ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their mind, either becauſe they haue vſed otherwiſe in their own country, or becauſe they haue ſeene another maner vſed in places where they haue travelled, which by how much the more it bee remote, by ſo much the more they doe eſteeme it, doe ſtirre vp ſuch contentious queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they thinke nothing right but what they doe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. And epiſt. 86. to the ſame effect. <hi>In his rebus in quibus nihil certi ſtatuit ſcriptura diuina, mos populi Dei, vel inſtituta maioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro lege tenenda ſunt.</hi> Here S. Auſtine tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth a farre better leſſon touching offence &amp; obſervance of orders of the Church, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many amongſt vs wil learne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> There are that holde ſome of the ceremonies of the Church lawful, but deny obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſome other, as ſome approue of kneeling at the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but deny the reſt; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e allow wearing the ſurplis, burial of the dead, yea &amp; the ring in marriage too, but not the croſſe in baptiſme, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
                  </label> This very argument is that which convinceth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: for a man may reaſon thus againſt them: Thoſe ceremonies which the falſly named Puritans hold to be lawfull, may and ought to bee vſed of every one, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their place in the Church: But the Puritans ſo called doe allow all the ceremonies eſtabliſhed in the Church.</p>
               <p>The aſſumption of this argument is proued by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15919:17"/> of particuler examples amongſt themſelues, who ſome allowing one &amp; ſome another, they do vnwitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their diuerſities, allow al, and yet all agree in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall point of diſobedience to the ceremonies of the Church,</p>
               <p>There are ſome out of pride, betake themſelues to this diſobedience for ſingularities ſake, and many ſeeing that in this floriſhing time, they had neither learning, pietie, nor any tolerable gifts to commend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, thinke by their refractarineſſe, to grow into note: for the people deſire novelty, and no novelty pleaſeth them better then that which tendeth to diſobedience: and let any one put on this perſon, he pleaſeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becommeth famous, muſt needs be learned, holy, &amp; haue al vertues in him. Some alſo by this meanes haue enriched themſelues and made a gaine of the time, haue ſuffered a little loſſe to haue a tenfold greater gaine in collections &amp; contributions, inſomuch that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being before poore pedants, are now beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e rich vſerers. And though ſome haue loſt much, yet many others haue gained much more. Now when the reward of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſhalbe greater then the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe of obedience, &amp; diſobedience being it ſelfe ſo pleaſing a humor, it muſt needs overſway many. The learneder ſort, I perſwade my ſelfe, doe eſpecially deny their obedience vnto the orders of the Church, becauſe they themſelues haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſpoken and preached againſt them, &amp; cannot now without offenſe to their people, whome formerly they haue ſo inſtructed; practiſe the contrary; elſe ſome of them haue profeſſed that to preach the Goſpell, in an vnknowne place, they could bee contented to vſe them. There is another ſort which are neither hot nor colde,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15919:17"/> yeeld obedience, and yeeld not obedience, humor al par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and ſtand in the middle betweene two opinions: That if the gouernement of the Church ſhould be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, according to the practiſes of many men, they might ſay; they were ever of that minde and therefore ſeldome or never vſed the ceremonies but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were vrged; nay ſpake againſt them privately and publikely as far as they durſt, yea humored, and moſt eſteemed ſuch men as did wholy deny the lawfulnes of them: and if the ſtate ſhall continue the preſent gouernement &amp; ceremonies, &amp; giue no way to <note n="y" place="margin">Aug. ipſa muta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio conſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis etiam quae adtuvat vtilitate novitate pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Formaliſts.</note> innovations, then they may ſay they hold with the doctrine diſcipline and ceremonies of the Church, they haue ſubſcribed vnto them, and yeelded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Church. Theſe men are vile formaliſts, that turne religion into policie, either condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in thoſe things they know, or knowingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme &amp; ſooth others in their errors and diſobedience. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither deſerue nor haue loue of Prince, Magiſtrate, nor people, neither is any truſt repoſed in them; for they cannot haue good conſciences which will ſtretch every way, and howſoever ſome for their owne purpoſe ſeem to flatter them: yet they are truely eſteemed of none. Yet God forbid that we ſhould deny, but there are ſome which deny obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed in the word of God; who if they could haue beene perſwaded otherwiſe, would never haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone ſuch evident loſſe and trouble; yet let ſuch labour to knowe that it is not good to leaue preaching of the word, a matter of ſubſtance which is commanded vnder a <hi>Woe,</hi> for matters of circumſtance, ceremonies, and in queſtion. And to conſider the benefit of vnity &amp; peace. The reaſon that the people alleadge, why they will not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15919:18"/> be brought to conforme themſelues in their places, nor like ſuch miniſters as are conformable, is, becauſe they haue beene otherwiſe taught, and they were good men that ſo taught vs, ſay they, And one holdes of Paul, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Apollo: Novelty and ſingularity doe ſo affect them, that they ſcorne to doe as the Church &amp; ſtate do: they ſay the ſmale number is in the right. The way that feweſt approue and moſt condemne, that is the true way. So did the Donatiſts plead in S. Auguſtines time, and becauſe ſome of them were then puniſhed for their outrageous faults, they grounded herevpon that they were the perſecuted Church, they ſuffered for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and yet the louing cariage and mildneſſe of the Church then towards them, and their proud, ſpitefull, and ſeditious practiſes againſt the Church; did evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie who were Chriſts diſciples and who not who had the ſpirit of loue and vnity, and who of pride hatred and contention. And I pray God we may once cleerely perceiue that this is the practiſe of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as Bucer ſaith) to bring vs to a verball profeſſion, and by queſtions of genealogies and matters of ſmaller moment, to tread S. Iames his religion vnder foot, when we ſhall haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, all in opinions, and little or never a whit in good workes, as is now come to paſſe. And all this while the Papiſts haue gotten greate advantage, and by whoſe meanes the Browniſts increaſe it is more then evident. and God grant we may knowe how God delighteth in loue and vnity, and how Church nor ſtate can longe conſiſt, where diviſions are foſtered.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Now becauſe all publique diſorders &amp; diſobedience, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe out of particuler houſes &amp; pariſhes; and that wee are met togither here at the Viſitation, for reformation of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15919:18"/> ſuch things as are amiſſe. The churchwardens &amp; ſworne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are to take heed that they performe obedience in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting faults according to their oath.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> But ſome obiect &amp; ſay they holde not our ſpiritual iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges nor their courtes lawfull, neither will they preſent for faults ſuch matters as they hold to bee no faults. i. diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto Church orders. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> To anſwere thee, why didſt thou ſweare to anſwere by oath particulerly to theſe and theſe things, and by thy mentall reſervation doeſt thus hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically &amp; wickedly diſpenſe with thy oath? Haſt thou learned divinity of the Priſcillianiſt, or of the treacherous equivocating Papiſt? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> Some will preſume they neede not preſent according to oath, becauſe little or nothing is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but a little purſe puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ: </seg>
               </label> May not the ſuperiour Magiſtrate repriue a fellon, and the ſupreme pardon at his pleaſure, yet thou muſt bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if thou do not apprehend &amp; indite ſuch offenders. And learne this withall, That Magiſtrates (eſpecially of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) do &amp; muſt do many things whereof we cannot tell the reaſon, and they may ſeeme to vs to doe ill when they do beſt; and it is not fit for vs to take accompt of them, but to looke to our owne duties, &amp; know they are more wiſe then we. And if in our buſines little be mended, that thou canſt ſee, imagine or hope that it is better then thou canſt ſee, and performe thou thy oath which is alwaies ſacred. Others diſpenſe with their oathes for feare, others ſpare their friends and familiars, others becauſe they would not be accompted troubleſome, and others alſo becauſe they would themſelues be borne with another time. Every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhould herein do wel to admoniſh his people of the great waight of an oath and if theſe and like vnder officers would preſent and indite according as they are bound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15919:19"/> need there not be ſuch exclaming againſt ſuperiorpowers for the raigning of all abuſes, ſeeing the principall cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from ourſelues. And thus much for the firſt point of obedience: and for this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Knowe that it will be expected at this autors hands, that he ſhould haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled theſe points more fully &amp; exactly, &amp; haue ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe in more plauſible &amp; poliſhed words &amp; ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: But vnderſtand that his ſtudy about this, was begun and ended within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of one onely weeke: beſides it was to be no larger then could be deliuered in an houres ſpace: and it was purpoſed only for the ſupply of that place, at that time, without any intent at all of further publiſhing, till their inordinate dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling extorted it out of his hands, and now is ſet downe as neere as may be in the ſame words. His intent was good, in Gods feare to perſwade them to obedience and vnity; which God grant that they and we all may follow. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15919:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
